Okay good.
בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody, happy eighth day of חנוכה, Chanukah, זאת
חנוכה, Zot Chanukah, and we pick up on second day of שבט,
Shvat, we pick up today is דף כב, Daf Kaf Bet, 22,
we pick up on כא עמוד ב Kaf Aleph Amud Beis in
the middle תא שמע Tashma about 15 lines before the lines get
wide. Okay, and we're in the middle of a discussion about the
whole debate about רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the תנא קמא Tana
Kama about when somebody takes an oath not to eat, do they
mean not to eat how eating is defined in normal areas of
the תורה Torah which is a כזית kezayis or do we assume
that since they said eat, and at least since an oath is
based on their words and not on some objective definition, and if
they said explicitly I won't eat even a tiny amount it would
mean a tiny amount, so when they just say I won't eat,
is then it also means just a tiny amount. So that's the
debate in the משנה. Mishna. Now the גמרא's Gemara question is that
there actually happens to be a position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
who says and you might remember from מכות Makkos that in general
when the תורה Torah prohibits eating something, it means a כל שהוא,
kol shehu, a small amount, and the amount of a כזית kezayis
is said only about the issue at least in terms of the
punishment of מלקות, malkus, of lashes. The amount of a כזית kezayis
is said only in terms of a קרבן. korban. So it wants
to know, maybe the reason רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that the
guy who makes the oath brings a קרבן korban even for a
small amount, is in general he defines eating to be a small
amount even for lashes and not because of something special about a
שבועה. shvuah. Obviously the משנה Mishna makes it sound that it's something
special about a שבועה, shvuah, but at least the גמרא's Gemara saying
maybe it's not so special. Now I want to say one word
about that because תוספות Tosafos asks and תוספות Tosafos says wait a
minute. Our משנה, Mishna, if you didn't remember the last two chapters
of the פרקים prakim of what we've been doing, is a focus
first is about sacrifices. When do you bring this sacrifice for entering
into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash when you're טמא, tamei, when do
you bring this sacrifice for violating your שבועה? shvuah? So therefore this
whole issue about when you say a פת-oriented pat שבועה shvuah do
you bring a sacrifice? So when רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva talks about
the issue about eating even a tiny amount, the initial issue is
not for getting lashes, the initial issue is for bringing a sacrifice.
So רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos both say, so why is the
גמרא Gemara saying that it should be maybe connected to רבי שמעון's
Rabbi Shimon idea that even a tiny amount for lashes? Because even
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that you need a כזית kezayis in
order to bring a קרבן, korban, so clearly it has nothing to
do with our discussion. Our discussion is a קרבן korban discussion. So
רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos has two answers. רש״י's Rashi is particularly
incisive. תוספות's Tosafos answer is a little more technical. תוספות's Tosafos answer
is the reason רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon normally says a tiny amount
for lashes and a כזית kezayis for קרבן korban is because for
קרבן korban is linked to כרת kares to getting which is this
heavy divine punishment. So therefore to be and the קרבן korban is
like the substitute for it when it was unintentional. So to be
worthy of this big heavy punishment of כרת kares you need a
כזית kezayis and that's why he says a כזית kezayis is for
a קרבן. korban. But for the קרבן korban for a שבועה, shvuah,
you don't get כרת kares for a שבועה, shvuah, even if you
willfully take a false oath, there's no כרת. kares. That's why it's
a little strange. You're bringing a קרבן korban for something that there's
no כרת kares associated with it. But תוספות Tosafos says because there's
no כרת kares associated with it, therefore if a tiny amount would
get you lashes, by a שבועה shvuah a tiny amount would also
bring a קרבן. korban. That's what תוספות Tosafos says. רש״י Rashi says
what I think is a very sort of incisive read. רש״י Rashi
says listen, if I eat I'm a little paraphrase. If I eat
a little bit of חזיר, chazer, it was a little bit of
an עבירה. aveirah. If I eat like a lot of חזיר, chazer,
it was a bigger עבירה, aveirah, a bigger sin. So therefore
Michael we could say that a little bit gets you one punishment
מלקות, malkus, a bigger amount gets you a different weightier punishment כרת
kares if you're intentional, קרבן korban if whatever. But there's a degree.
You could understand that כזית kezayis is a bigger sin than a
small amount. That's normally. But רש״י Rashi says think about the case
of a שבועה. shvuah. I take an oath I won't
eat. If I eat a tiny amount and I get lashes, what
are we saying? We're saying that I won't eat means I won't
eat even a tiny amount. And when I eat a tiny amount,
I have violated my שבועה, shvuah, right? That's the problem with a
שבועה. shvuah. So רש״י Rashi says the problem is not that the
bread I said I won't eat is טרף treif and if I
ate a lot of bread I did a worse sin. The problem
is that the act I did breaks my word, right? That's the
problem with a שבועה. shvuah. So רש״י Rashi says once the act
breaks your word, you didn't break your word more or less. You
broke your word. Eating a lot more of the thing isn't a
bigger breaking of the word. Once you broke your word, you broke
your word. So I think it's a very insightful point, right? When
you eat more of the thing, if the problem is eating the
thing, more of the thing is a bigger sin. But if the
problem is breaking your word, then eating... more of the thing is
not a bigger breaking of your word. Okay, so that's the way
רש"י Rashi frames it. Either way what the גמרא Gemara says is
because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that you get even lashes for
a small amount by normal sins, maybe that's what's informing רבי עקיבא's
Rabbi Akiva's position that you bring a קרבן korban for a
שבועה shvua even if you only eat a tiny amount to break
your שבועה. shvua. Or is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva saying no, normally
you wouldn't get lashes for a tiny amount, but שבועה shvua is
special. Since שבועה shvua is based on your word, maybe here since
you said I won't eat, you meant even a tiny amount. Yeah,
a couple of things.
One is I mean I like the idea that you have to
eat a little bit, like חזיר, chazir, it's much worse to eat
a lot than a little, but after a כזית kezayit הלכה halacha
doesn't view it as any worse or not, right? Right, so a
pound is the same thing as eating an ounce. Doesn't you know,
so I mean you'd still think that it should be worse and
worse and worse, but it isn't.
We don't have gradations on every little thing, but you can have
some gradations.
And the other thing is, in terms of, but הלכה halacha has
no problem defining what is an act of eating in so many
other places. In other words you broke your word, okay well הלכה
halacha has no problem saying your word means eating, an act of
eating which is a כזית.
kezayit. Right, which is what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds. Okay,
but the point, רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva's point is that since you
can frame it, you could say I won't eat 2.3 ounces, you
could say I won't eat a tiny amount. So should we by
default say if you're not specific you go by the generic explanation
the תורה Torah normally has, that's what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
holds? Or do we say no, we try to assume like we'll
interpret it in the sense of since you said eating we'll interpret
it in the minimalist sense and we'll try to assume that that's
what you meant, you meant even the tiniest amount.
Yeah, one other question in the definition of eating in terms of
like on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Right. It's not a כזית. kezayit.
But that's not about eating, that's about breaking the fast and about
exactly. So יום כיפור Yom Kippur is an exception.
Oh I was going to say it's not a, in other words
the eating has to be a certain amount, right? So does that
contradict רש"י Rashi saying if you broke your word about eating because
well no that just gets back to רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva's point,
exactly. Okay so let's take a look. תא שמע דאמרו ליה לרבי
עקיבא. Ta shema deamru lei leRabbi Akiva. So they said to רבי
עקיבא: Rabbi Akiva: היכן מצינו באוכל כל שהוא חייב שזה חייב? heichan
matzinu beocheil kol shehu chayav shezeh chayav?
Where do we ever find that even a smallest amount is חייב?
chayav? And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says yeah but שבועות shvuot are
different. That's basically רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva's answer. ואי סלקא דעתך Vei
isalka deita if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in general holds that even
a small amount is a transgression, לימא להו leima lehu say back
to them: אנא בכל התורה כולה כרבי שמעון סבירא לי. ana bechol
hatorah kulei keRabbi Shimon sevira li. Yeah what do you mean where
do we find a small amount? I always hold a small amount
you're חייב. chayav. So clearly since he didn't say that, he normally
holds you need a lot but שבועות shvuot are different or a
כזית. kezayit. And the גמרא Gemara says no, not necessarily, לדבריהם דרבנן
קאמר. ledivreiham deRabbanan ka'amar. He's saying back to the רבנן Rabbanan within
your position I will respond to you. לדידי Ledidi as far as
I'm concerned בכל התורה כולה כרבי שמעון סבירא לי. bechol hatorah kulei
keRabbi Shimon sevira li. I don't think שבועות shvuot are different. Maybe
I think that normally even a small amount is a violation. Okay,
so I don't think שבועות shvuot are different. לדידכו Ledidchu but you
who normally think you need a כזית, kezayit, הודו לי מיהא odu
li miha at least you should concede to me that even if
normally you need a כזית, kezayit, you should concede to me by
a שבועה shvua it should be even the smallest amount. הודו לי
מיהא הא מפרש חייב סתם נמי חייב. odu li miha ha umefareish
chayav stam nami chayav. Since if you were explicit and said a
tiny amount it would be prohibited, so even if you're not explicit
we should read that into your words. ואמרו ליה רבנן לא. Ve'amru
lei Rabbanan lo. I love that answer. The רבנן Rabbanan said no.
Pshooh! Like you don't have to explain it like oh well shouldn't
you admit that this should be the same as that? No. Alright
anyway, so no points on a debating team for that answer, but
okay the point is like why should I make that assumption. Okay,
תא שמע ta shema come and hear. רבי עקיבא אומר נזיר ששרה
פיתו ביין. Rabbi Akiva omer nazir shesharah pitto beyayin. If a נזיר
nazir dipped his bread in wine and ויש בו veyesh bo and
he can't drink wine, ויש בו כדי לצרף כזית. veyesh bo kedei
letzaref kezayit. Now if you add the bread plus the amount of
wine it is a כזית's kezayit's worth. But the actual wine is
not the minimum amount, it's the whole combination that's the minimum amount.
Okay, so nevertheless you're חייב. chayav. This is a general principle that
היתר מצטרף לאיסור heter mitztaref leissur that even the non-prohibited thing combines
to the prohibited thing. It's a specific הלכה halacha by נזיר. nazir.
Okay, but the point is he needs it to combine to a
כזית, kezayit, so clearly רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva holds that you normally
need an olive's worth. By נזיר nazir there's a special way to
compute the olive's worth, but the normal rule is you need an
olive's worth in order to transgress. ואי סלקא דעתך דאמר כרבי שמעון
סבירא לי Vei isalka deitach de'amar keRabbi Shimon sevira li if he
normally holds like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, למה לי לצרף? lama lei
letzaref?
Why does he need to combine? Right, even a small amount. Okay,
that's a pretty darn good proof that he normally holds you need
a
כזית. kezayit. ותנן Ve'otnan and we also have another משנה. Mishnah. שבועה
שלא אוכל ואכל נבילות וטריפות שקצים ורמשים. Shvua shelo ocheil ve'achal neveilot
utreifot shekatzim uremasim. Somebody takes a general oath I won't eat. I
won't eat anything and then they go ahead and they eat some
נבילות neveilot and טריפות, treifot, שקצים ורמשים, shekatzim uremasim, חזיר, chazir, נבילה,
neveilah, etc., חייב. chayav. So that's included in eating. Eating doesn't just
mean eating kosher stuff, eating means eating anything and they would violate
their שבועה shvua in addition to violating the biblical prohibition. רבי שמעון
פוטר, Rabbi Shimon poter, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon exempts. והוינן בה Ve'avinan
bah and we ask on this משנה, Mishnah, this is a משנה
Mishnah coming up end of today if we get to it. אמאי
חייב? Amay chayav? Why is he חייב? chayav? מושבע ועומד מהר סיני
הוא. Mushba ve-omed me-Har Sinai hu. He is already forsworn from הר
סיני. Har Sinai. Since he's already told on הר סיני Har Sinai
not to eat these things, and that's considered like we all sort
of took an שבועה shavuah there. So it's a principle that one
שבועה shavuah doesn't sort of you know if there's already a pre-existing
שבועה shavuah that says you must do something or you must not
do something, another שבועה shavuah won't take effect on top of it.
Even to reinforce it, not only not we're not talking about to
contradict it, even to reinforce it, it's called you know he's already
מושבע ועומד. mushba ve-omed. אין שבועה חלה על שבועה. Ein shvua chal
al shvua. A שבועה shvua doesn't take effect on top of another
one. Multiple, right? Okay whatever, we'll get to
that. So that's our question, why do you transgress by eating this
טריפה treifa food, the שבועה shvua should not have been binding in
this regard. So now there's different answers to this. רב ושמואל ורבי
יוחנן דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav ve-Shmuel ve-Rabbi Yochanan damri travaihu, actually it's not
תרווייהו travaihu it's תלתייהו, tlasaihu, but the phrase is always תרווייהו. travaihu.
So תלתייהו, tlasaihu, the three of them. Okay רב Rav and שמואל
Shmuel and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan they all say בכולל דברים המותרים
עם האסורים, bekolel devarim hamutarim im ha-asurim, what Michael said. Since you
said I won't eat anything, so since the שבועה shvua takes effect
on all the world's kosher food, it also takes effect on the
non-kosher. Since if it was just about non-kosher food it would be
redundant and not effective. But since it's about all food in the
world, it also takes effect on the non-kosher food. That's one answer.
ריש לקיש אמר, Reish Lakish amar, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says, אי
אתה מוצא, ee atta motze, you cannot find this case that it
would that would not help. It wouldn't make a difference, it still
wouldn't take effect. You cannot take effect on non-kosher food except in
the following example. אלא אי במפרש חצי שיעור. Ella ee bimfaresh chatzi
shiur. You explicitly say that a שבועה shvua I won't eat even
a חצי כזית. chatzi k'zayit. Oh, well since you said a חצי
כזית, chatzi k'zayit, that now takes effect even on חזיר. chazir. And
we don't say you're already forsworn. Because you're forsworn in the תורה
Torah not to eat a כזית k'zayit of חזיר. chazir. You wouldn't
violate in the תורה Torah if you ate a half of a
כזית. k'zayit. So since your שבועה shvua meant not to eat a
half of the כזית, k'zayit, that does take effect. That would be
one example. אי במפרש חצי שיעור ואליבא דרבנן, Ee bimfaresh chatzi shiur
ve-aliba de-rabbanan, and according to the רבנן rabbanan who say that normally
if you just say you won't eat, you mean a כזית, k'zayit,
so then you'd have to be explicit and say a חצי שיעור.
chatzi shiur. אי בסתם ואליבא דרבי עקיבא, Ee bistem ve-aliba de-Rabbi Akiva,
or according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva it would work. If you
say I won't eat חזיר, chazir, so then eat means for רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva even a small amount, but you're not מושבע ועומד
mushba ve-omed from the תורה's Torah perspective, you'd only violate with a
כזית. k'zayit. So therefore when you say you won't eat, according to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that means even a tiny amount, that does
take effect, that prohibits you more than the תורה's Torah prohibition. Okay.
דאמר אדם אוסר עצמו בכל שהוא, De-amar adam oser atzmo bekolshehu, even
a small amount. Now that makes it pretty clear though that normally
you need a כזית k'zayit and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying
that a שבועה shvua is even more strict and a שבועה shvua
is even a small amount. So that's what גמרא Gemara says. ואי
סלקא דעתך בעלמא כרבי שמעון סבירא ליה, Ve-ee salka daatach be-alma ke-Rabbi
Shimon sevira lei, and if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva generally held like
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that no even a small amount, כל שהוא
נמי מושבע ועומד מהר סיני הוא. kolshehu nami mushba ve-omed me-Har Sinai
hu. So even a small amount he'd already be forsworn. This is
very clear that it means no, before your שבועה shvua was only
a כזית k'zayit and your שבועה shvua made it a small amount.
Okay. אלא לאו שמע מינה דבעלמא כרבנן סבירא ליה, Ella lav shema
mina de-alma ke-rabbanan sevira lei, that from all of this you see
it's very clear בעלמא כרבנן סבירא ליה be-alma ke-rabbanan sevira lei that
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in general holds that you need a full
כזית k'zayit in order to transgress, שמע מינה shema mina that it's
a good proof. And it's only by שבועה, shvua, since שבועה's shvua
about violating your word, now we do have to say when your
word said I won't eat what you meant by eat. So but
then already it's not necessarily since you could say I won't eat
even a tiny amount. So that model to create an איסור שבועה
issur shvua of a tiny amount exists. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is
saying therefore we're going to interpret your words that way. Now it's
not totally clear why we do. Do we assume since you aren't
explicating you meant even the smallest amount, or do we assume that
that's just the normal vernacular, when people say I won't eat anything
they don't mean a כזית, k'zayit, people don't talk in הלכה halakha
terminology. Is it that if we don't know how to interpret your
words we'll just adopt the most strict meaning of them? It doesn't
really explain. But the point is since we know that model exists
of a שבועה shvua to apply to even a small amount, that's
what we're going to say that even when you're not clear that
that's what you meant, even when you're not explicit. Yes, Charles?
I was going to ask about the idea חצי שיעור. chatzi shiur.
Yeah, so תוספות Tosafot raises that, what do you mean that even
a small amount you're not forsworn in the תורה Torah according to
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan even though you don't get lashes for a
כזית, k'zayit, but you do violate if you eat less than a
כזית. k'zayit. So תוספות Tosafot raises that question and תוספות Tosafot sort
of says well the question's what do you violate. Is it like
you transgress the prohibition of not eating חזיר, chazir, it's just you're
not worthy of a punishment? If we would say that, then it
really would be a question, then you are מושבע ועומד. mushba ve-omed.
When the תורה Torah said don't eat חזיר chazir it meant even
a small amount. But so that actually would is a good
question. An answer could be that if I eat a חצי כזית
chatzi k'zayit of חזיר chazir I didn't violate the תורה's Torah verse
don't eat חזיר, chazir, I violated this generic idea that I shouldn't
eat even small amounts of איסור. issur. So because that's not really
a strict פסוק, pasuk, a strict like you know an explicit prohibition,
it's just some generic idea even if it's דאורייתא. de-oraita. Biblically oriented,
it's not in the category of מיושב בדעתו. mushav bedaato. So that's
sort of תוספות'ס Tosafot's answer. Okay, let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara.
אמר ליה לרבי עקיבא היכא מצינו? Amar lei le'Rabbi Akiva heicha matzinu?
So we're still staying in the thick of this debate with רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay, so they said to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
how can you say even a small amount? You know, you never
transgress for a small amount. And he said, yeah, but שבועה shvua
is different. Basically as we said, שבועה shvua you could explicitly say
a small amount if you wanted to. So the גמרא Gemara says
ולא? v'lo? What do you mean that the rabbis say we never
find you transgress for a small amount? והרי נמלה, ve'harei nemala, if
you eat an ant you transgress, even though it's a tiny little
ant. בריה שאני. Birya shani. When it's a whole unit, it's different.
A whole unit, a whole ant is significant. Okay, there's actually two
explanations why בריה birya is different. Either because it gives it qualitative
significance the same way a כזית kezayit gives something quantitative significance. A
בריה birya gives it qualitative significance. You did something of meaning. You
ate a whole animal. Okay, the other explanation is because it's an
explicit, explicitly what the verse says. If the verse says don't eat
a שקץ sheketz or a שרץ sheretz and don't eat an עכבר
achbar or whatever it is, and I ate a whole עכבר, achbar,
it's exactly what the verse says, right? When the verse says don't
eat meat, you want to say how much meat? Right? It's not
clear because that's like, that's not well defined. But when it says
don't eat a rat, okay, I ate a rat. Even if it's
a tiny rat, I ate a rat. What?
No, but you could get to
eat the whole pig based on that. Well, that's why the חידוש
chiddush is that there's even a דין din of a כזית. kezayit.
Okay, that's true, that's not explicit in the verse. But when you
eat a whole thing that is less than a כזית, kezayit, then
you clearly have transgressed. Okay, so that's בריה שאני. birya shani. והרי
הקדש, ve'harei hekdesh, one minute the גמרא Gemara says, how about הקדש?
hekdesh? If you get הנאה hana'ah from הקדש, hekdesh, that's מעילה, me'ila,
even less than a כזית. kezayit. גמרא Gemara says, okay, but הבעינן
שוה פרוטה. habinan shaveh prutah. That doesn't mean that there's no שיעור,
shiur, it just means the measurement is different. That's about getting benefit
and benefit we measure by a penny's worth of benefit, but that
doesn't fundamentally mean that there's no minimum amount, it's just a different
scale. והרי מפרש, ve'harei mefaresh, what about רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's point,
which is if you explicitly say I won't eat a כזית, kezayit,
I won't eat a tiny amount? So that's an example the rabbis
agree that you transgress with a tiny amount? So the גמרא Gemara
says, so how come they say to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, we
never find that you transgress with a tiny amount?
You mean by the default option.
Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says back, right? מפרש
נמי כבריה דמי, mefaresh nami k'birya dami, that's like a בריה. birya.
Why is that like a בריה? birya? So it depends on the
two explanations we gave about בריה. birya. If בריה birya is about
that it gives it significance because it's a whole thing, so by
you explicitly saying normally a tiny amount is trivial, it's a meaningless
act. But if you say I won't eat a tiny amount, you've
given that act weight. You've given it significance. Okay, but as Michael
says, by default, so yes, fine, that's what the rabbis are saying.
All of these are explanations, those are exceptions. By default, eating means
something significant means a כזית. kezayit. If you chose to explicitly name
it and give it weight, that gives it weight. But by default,
it's not a meaningful act. So the other explanation that it is
similar to a בריה birya is like I said before. If the
תורה Torah says don't eat a rat and you ate a rat,
you did exactly violated exactly what the תורה Torah said, even if
it was a tiny little baby rat, less than a כזית. kezayit.
But or don't eat an ant. But so similarly if I said
I won't eat a tiny amount and I eat a tiny amount,
I have violated exactly what I said. So that's exactly like the
תורה Torah said don't eat a rat and I ate a rat.
So that's why it's like a בריה. birya. Okay, but again, the
default is not that way. If you just generically say I won't
eat, then a tiny amount is trivial. And that's the rabbis' response
to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. והרי עפר, ve'harei afar, let's say you
say I won't eat dirt. Okay, there's actually a condition like that,
right? What's it called? Pica? Is that right? There's some condition that
people need to eat dirt. Anyway, nobody knows what I'm talking about?
Pica? You don't know what I'm talking about? Okay, anyway, so if
somebody says I won't eat dirt, רבא Rava asks a question. Since
there's not eating dirt is a bizarre act, like would you even
call it eating like when you put dirt in your mouth? Okay,
so maybe it shouldn't go by the normal definitions of eating. And
therefore in that case maybe it even means a tiny amount. Okay,
because it's not like it's a normal act of eating. So אלא,
ella, since the גמרא Gemara apparently the rabbis hold that there's never
an example of a small amount, תפשוט דבעי רבא, tifshot d'bei Rava,
can we conclude an answer to רבא'ס Rava's question? What was רבא'ס
Rava's question? Because רבא Rava said שבועה שלא אוכל ואכל עפר, shvua
shelo ochel v'achal afar, it's actually שבועה שלא אכל עפר ואכל shvua
shelo achal afar v'achal בכמה. bekama. If somebody takes an oath they
won't eat dirt and they ate,
and רבא Rava said how much? Is it a tiny amount or
would it still go by a כזית? kezayit? So since the rabbis
say we never find a tiny amount, presumably they would hold that
even in the dirt case it would be a כזית. kezayit. So
the גמרא Gemara says תפשוט עד דאיכא כזית, tifshot ad de'ika kezayit,
should we conclude therefore until it's a כזית? kezayit? Because otherwise there
would have been an example of a tiny amount. So the גמרא
Gemara says no. כי קאמרינן במידי דבר אכילה קאמרינן. ki amrinan be'midi
de'bar achila ka'amrinan.
No, no, no, that's not a point. The whole reason there it
might mean a tiny amount is because it's not a normal thing
that's being eaten. So that's the rabbis' point. When something is a
normal food that's a normal act of eating is being done to,
we never find it's less than a כזית. kezayit. It doesn't mean...
that there are bizarre things like eating dirt that wouldn't have some
different
definition. Okay, והרי קונמות? ve-harei konamos? How about קונם? konam? קונם konam
is like a type of a נדר, neder, but it's a נדר
neder that draws directly on קרבנות. korbanos. If I take here let's
assume this is a loaf of bread and I say קונם konam
this bread alive. קונם konam is actually almost it's like a euphemism
for the word קרבן. korban. I make this bread forbidden with a
נדר neder as if it were a קרבן. korban. And the גמרא
Gemara thinks that because I use a word קונם konam which is
like a word of קרבן korban or like a הקדש, hekdesh, okay,
so it could be first of all that there's actually מעילה, me'ilah,
I would actually transgress the prohibitions of benefiting from הקדש. hekdesh. We're
going to get to about that in a minute, okay. But anyway,
but maybe the גמרא Gemara says even a tiny amount I would
transgress similar to like transgressing הקדש, hekdesh, even a tiny amount. So
that would be another example where I would eat something and it
would be a tiny amount. Why do the rabbis say we never
have it? So the גמרא Gemara says קונמות נמי כמפורש דמי. konamos
nami kemiforash dami. That's like you were explicit. Why is it like
you were explicit? Because רש"י Rashi says I don't say קונם konam
this is אסור assur for me to eat. I just say this
is קונם. konam. So this is קונם konam like this is taboo,
almost like the word חרם cherem in the תורה, Torah, like completely
off limits. So since I'm not fundamentally focusing on the act of
eating, it's not defined by an act of eating so it doesn't
have a כזית. kazayis. Now that being said, you know you should
have said that if you're similar to like הקדש, hekdesh, it should
still be defined by like a שוה פרוטה, shaveh prutah, which is
what תוספות Tosfos says. Why should it be stricter than הקדש? hekdesh?
Even if it was literal הקדש hekdesh there would be some way
of measuring what does it mean to violate, right? A penny's worth,
right? It might not be fundamentally about an act of eating, it
might be fundamentally about deriving benefit, but still there's some measure. So
it is funny that the גמרא Gemara thinks sounds like קונם konam
could be weightier than הקדש. hekdesh. But the bottom line is that
if it's based on that קרבן korban or הקדש hekdesh model, it
fundamentally is not about eating.
What says what says was the answer?
He doesn't give an answer. He just leaves that as a question.
Okay, Charlie you found out what's the name of the condition is?
No, still looking. Still looking?
Okay, but there's a whole list of things on Google that say
that eating dirt is good for you.
Really? I
think it's called what's pica? What's pica?
Pica is an
animal.
No, craving and chewing substances that have no nutritional value such as
ice, clay, soil, or paper. Pica. Okay, moving
up. Okay, אמר ליה היכא מצינו במדבר ומביא קרבן שזה מדבר ומביא
קרבן. amar lei heicha mazinu bemidaber umevi korban shezeh midaber umevi korban.
So רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's answer is, so the rabbis are saying
look, there're some exceptions that the גמרא Gemara mentioned, but they are
all irrelevant. Normally eating means eating something substantive which substantial which means
a כזית. kazayis. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, okay, but this
is also case an exception. Now the better example of an exception
is the ברייתא beraisa the גמרא Gemara quoted where it's an exception
because you could explicitly say a כל שהוא, kol shehu, so even
when you're not explicit that's what we're going to interpret you to
have said. That makes sense. But in the משנה Mishnah רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva makes a different point. His point is here this case
is very weighty because you violate just through your words. You bring
a קרבן korban just by doing something with your words. And we
never find a קרבן korban with just your words. So the question
is okay, but why is that relevant to a כל שהוא? kol
shehu? Like so תוספות Tosfos just says it's like a very abstract
argument. Since this is a weighty transgression that the תורה Torah is
very like sort of, you know, the punishment or whatever the consequences
are very weighty, it makes you bring a קרבן korban just for
something with your words which normally it wouldn't do, so therefore we're
going to interpret everything in a weighty way. And we're going to
say that when you say you won't eat, we're going to interpret
it in the weightiest way to mean even a tiny amount. רש"י,
Rashi, you know that's not a very convincing argument. רש"י Rashi reads
it in a different way. רש"י Rashi reads it as it's not
so much that it's weighty because that you bring a קרבן korban
is proof that it's a weighty thing, but no, the focus of
the issue with a קרבן korban is the violating of your words.
And since the focus is your words, so the question is not
what does אכילה achila normally mean, but what did your words mean?
And since it's about violating your words, since your words could mean
a כל שהוא kol shehu or maybe we assume they do, then
you've already violated even with a כל שהוא. kol shehu. Okay, so
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. ולא? velo? Now the
גמרא Gemara says really? Are there no cases of bringing a קרבן
korban when you just did something with your
words? והרי מגדף? ve-harei megadef? How about somebody that curses God? Okay,
now it's not clear that there would be a קרבן korban there,
but we're assuming it would, according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva actually
there is a קרבן. korban. Okay, if he did it בשוגג, beshogeg,
right? I don't know how somebody exactly does that בשוגג, beshogeg, maybe
they thought it was מותר mutar to do.
I don't
know.
מדבר ועושה קאמרינן. medaber ve'oseh kamrinan. The גמרא Gemara says alright, but
that's not exactly the same case. That's that that act of speech
itself is the violation. What we're talking about is that your act
of speech creates a prohibition on you. It forbids something on you.
If you say a שבועה shvuah I won't eat, then my speech
has made it forbidden. So that's our question. Where would you bring
a קרבן korban where it's about violating your words? Not where the
words itself is the violation. is the violation, but where the act
of violating your words brings a קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara
says והאי מדבר וחוטא הוא. vehai medaber vechote hu. Oh, and in
the case of מגדף, Megadef, you're sinning with your words immediately. גמרא
Gemara says one minute, והא מנזיר. veha minazir. How about a נזיר?
Nazir? You say words and then you bring a קרבן korban at
the end of your נזירות. nezirut. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
that's maybe קרבנו על דיבורו קאמינא. korbano al diburo kamina. We're saying
that the reason for the קרבן korban is because you violated your
words. והאי מאי קרבן לאשתרויי חמרא הוא דקמייתי. vehai mai korban leishtruyei
chamra hu dekamayti. But a נזיר Nazir is bringing a קרבן korban
because to end his נזירות. nezirut. The קרבן korban is a consequence
of your words, but it's not somehow because of violating your words.
Okay.
Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says והרי הקדש. veharei hekdesh. How about if
I sanctify something and then get benefit from it? That's a
קרבן מעילה. korban meilah. And that's a קרבן korban about violating
my words. So the גמרא Gemara says אוסר לעצמו קאמינא. oser le'atzmo
kamina. No, no. הקדש Hekdesh creates an objective reality. It makes something
forbidden on everyone. So it creates like a status. Okay. And then
you violated the status. You made this thing into a
קרבן korban and then you violated its קרבן korban status. Okay, so
that, yes, can your words create a certain objective metaphysical reality, like
this thing is sanctified and now nobody can benefit from it, and
then you bring a קרבן korban because of this objective status? Sure,
that we can have. But we're talking about אוסר לעצמו. oser le'atzmo.
והאי אוסר כל העולם כולו הוא. vehai oser kol ha'olam kulo hu.
So when I say a שבועה shevua I won't do something, that
doesn't create an objective status, right? I mean the גמרא Gemara is
making a very good point, right? If I sort of say I
have bound myself with my words, but as opposed to something like
נזיר Nazir or הקדש hekdesh or those types of things, right? Those
actually, I mean even a נזיר Nazir for example, I'm a נזיר
Nazir vis-a-vis you. Like you would transgress if you force-fed me wine.
You would transgress if you put me into a cemetery. Okay, so
נזיר Nazir and הקדש hekdesh create statuses and then you bring a
קרבן korban for violating the status. Okay, but by a שבועה shevua
it's just this sense of I'm bound by my words and I
violate my words, not that my words create a status. Okay, and
therefore the גמרא Gemara says that is a unique phenomenon. So the
גמרא Gemara says one
minute, והרי קונמות. veharei konamos. So we're reviewing what we did before.
How about if you say קונם konam this bread is אסור asur
to me? That's not a status vis-a-vis everybody else. It's just a
status makes it forbidden to me. Now still, I would still say
that's still a status. It's not just being bound by my words,
it's my words creating a status. But the גמרא Gemara is saying
that's already getting pretty similar, okay? That's like something that only relates
to you in
particular. קסבר אין מעילה בקרבנות. kasavar ein meilah bekorbanos. There's no קרבן
korban for קונמות, konamos, there's just a debate and therefore we still
don't have a קרבן. korban. So what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
is this case is unique. This is the only case in the
תורה Torah where you bring a קרבן korban for violating your words.
Sometimes yes, your words are transgression. I'm not talking about that. Sometimes
your words create statuses. I'm not talking about that. This is the
only case where you bring a קרבן korban for violating your words.
Okay, and therefore I'm going to say that your words here mean
even a כזית. kezayit. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, now we're going to get to explaining
what is the scope of their debate. אמר רבא מחלוקת בסתם. Amar
Rava machlokes bistsam. Their debate is when you just said I won't
eat without clarifying how
much. אבל במפרש דברי הכל בכל שהוא הוא. aval bimefaresh divrei hakol
bechol shehu hu. But if you say it explicitly, okay, then everybody
would agree that it's even the smallest amount, which is what we've
been assuming. We've actually been saying that that would have been a
better way of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva articulating his position. Since you
guys agree to me with a small amount, you should agree to
me even if you're not
explicit. So מאי טעמא מפרש נמי כבריה דמי. mai ta'ama mefaresh nami
kiberiah dami. It's interesting that we have to explain it that way,
right? Because we're explicit, it's like a בריה. beriah. It's like it
gives it weight. The easier way to explain it is because it
was explicit, you violated your words. You could say anything, right? You
could say I won't do a triple somersault. You could take a
שבועה shevua you know that whatever, that you won't scratch your back.
So you could take a שבועה shevua that you won't eat a
tiny amount. So presumably that's what the גמרא Gemara means when it
says כבריה דמי, kiberiah dami, but it's funny that it has to
use בריה beriah as the example. Okay, clearly everybody should agree with
when you're explicit and that presumably is what informs רבי עקיבא's Rabbi
Akiva position that even when you're not explicit, that's what you mean.
Okay, ואמר רבא מחלוקת בשלא אוכל. ve'amar Rava machlokes beshelo ochel. The
debate is when you use the word I won't eat. Eat classically
for the Rabbis means a כזית. kezayit. אבל בשלא אטעום, aval beshelo
et'om,
if I say I won't taste anything, דברי הכל בכל שהוא. divrei
hakol bechol shehu. Everybody would agree that taste means even a small
amount and there's no halachic definition of taste, so the Rabbis can't
plug that into some pre-existing definition, so we'll say that. means a
small amount. So פשיטא pshita says גמרא Gemara obviously? No. מהו דתימא
mahu d'teima I might have thought
ליטום נמי litom nami כדאמרי אינשי k'd'amrei inshi even when you say
or at like I'll taste, it's also like when people say, hey,
let's have a, let's have a taste. And people sometimes say taste
they don't mean a tiny amount, they maybe mean like they don't
really mean okay you're יצא, yotzei, you had a taste. Just says,
oh I made a nice, I just made an apple cake, would
you like to have a taste? Sure. Okay here, and then he
gives you like a tiny little amount, there, I gave you a
taste. What? You said you were going to give me some. So
anyway, so taste maybe? But the Mishnah says no, it is true
that taste could mean more substantial, but taste could also mean a
tiny amount, and I would say even in particular since there's no
halachic category of that taste means X amount, we'll interpret it in
the small amount version. But when you say eat, there's a halachic
definition of that and we're going to apply the
halachic definition. Okay. Okay. Now, אמר רב פפא,
amar Rav Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa says מחלוקת בשבועות, machlokes
b'shavuos, מחלוקת machlokes if a guy says בשבועה bishvua that he won't
eat. אבל בקונמות aval b'konamos if you say קונם konam this is
forbidden to me, דברי הכל בכל שהוא divrei hakol b'khol shehu everybody
would agree even the small amount, and that's what we were asking
on based earlier, that when you say קונם konam it's even a
small amount. Because מאי טעמא mai ta'ama why? קונמות נמי konamos nami
כיון דלא קמדכר שמא דאכילה keivan d'lo kamadkar shma d'achila we sort
of was the גמרא Gemara earlier was borrowing on this. Since you
don't say קונם konam this bread is forbidden for me to eat,
you just say קונם konam this bread is forbidden, so forbidden means
absolutely and in all ways and you don't have to do something
that's defined as an act of eating. כמיפרש דמי, k'mifaresh dami, it's
like you made it explicit. Now yes, it wouldn't just be limited
to eating, it would also be included in benefit, and that's of
course what תוספות Tosafos says. Okay fine, there's not a כזית, kazayit,
but it should still be a פרוטה, pruta, it should still be
a penny's worth, it shouldn't be more weighty than הקדש, hekdesh, and
תוספות Tosafos doesn't really have an answer to that. Maybe the answer
is אינהכי נמי, ein hachi nami, but the גמרא Gemara makes it
sound like there's no minimum amount in any way. Okay. מיתיבי. Meisive.
Now I'm going to ask you, now we're going to focus in
on this last argument that the word קונם konam means even a
tiny amount and does not go by a כזית. kazayit. שני קונמות
מצטרפין, shnei konamos mitztarfin, שתי שבועות אין מצטרפות. shtei shevuos ein mitztarfos.
So let's say I say, let's assume that these are both pieces
of bread, okay, or apples, and I say קונם konam this apple's
forbidden to me and קונם konam this apple's forbidden to me. And
then I have a half of a כזית kazayit of this apple
and a half of a כזית kazayit of this apple. So that
combines and I've now transgressed and I would bring a קרבן korban
or get מלקות malkus or whatever. Okay. However, if I say שבועה
shvua and then the person says that he won't eat this apple
and then he says שבועה shvua that he won't eat this apple
and then he eats a half of a כזית kazayit of each,
he does not bring a קרבן. korban. Okay. So it's not clear
what the difference is, but the relevant, and we'll explore what the
difference is, but the relevant point is is that there's a minimum
amount by קונם. konam. You know, and they don't combine. The fact
that you need them to combine means that there's a minimum amount.
Okay so let's take a look. Or actually they do combine by
a קונם, konam, they don't combine by a שבועה. shvua. But either
way, the fact that by קונם konam they combine, by שבועה shvua
they don't, but the fact that you need them to combine shows
that we're dealing with a minimum amount. Okay so תא שמע ta
shema come and hear. I'm sorry, מיתיבי. Meisive. שני קונמות מצטרפין, shnei
konamos mitztarfin, קונם konam this and קונם konam that and you eat
a little bit of each, they combine. שתי שבועות אין מצטרפות shtei
shevuos ein mitztarfos but a שבועה shvua this and שבועה shvua that
they don't combine. רבי מאיר אומר Rabbi Meir omer קונמות כשבועות, konamos
k'shavuos, קונם konam is just like a שבועה shvua and in both
cases they do not presumably they do not combine. Now, ואי סלקא
דעתך חייב בכל שהוא v'i salka da'atach chayav b'khol shehu the גמרא
Gemara challenges רב פפא, Rav Pappa, if it's true that a קונם
konam you transgress even the smallest amount, למה לי לצרף? lama li
l'tzaref? Why would I need to combine them? Forget what the difference
of קונם konam and שבועה shvua is, the fact that you need
to combine shows that there is a minimum amount. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, דאמר אכילה מזו עלי קונם אכילה מזו עלי קונם.
d'amar achila mizu alai konam achila mizu alai konam. So remember, the
גמרא Gemara explained רב פפא Rav Pappa that the reason קונם konam
doesn't have a minimum amount is because you didn't use the word
אכילה. achila. And since you didn't say eat, we say therefore even
a tiny thing. So רב פפא Rav Pappa would say fine, this
is a case where you were explicit. קונם konam this bread is
forbidden to me in eating and קונם konam this bread is forbidden
to me in eating. So in that case where you explicitly say
the word of eating, then then
you do need a כזית kazayit and then we have this הלכה
halacha that two קונמות konamos combine and two שבועות shevuos do not
combine. So fine we've solved the problem on רב פפא, Rav Pappa,
now let's explain this difference between קונם konam and שבועה. shvua. Why
does the combination work differently? Okay so let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. אי הכי ei hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, אי
הכי אמאי מצטרפו, ei hachi amai mitztarfo, סוף סוף זיל להכא ליכא
שיעורא זיל להכא ליכא שיעורא sof sof zil l'hacha lika shiura zil
l'hacha lika shiura which the גמרא Gemara guess could have asked anyway
but it's asking with this answer. If I say קונם konam this
is forbidden to me eating and קונם konam this is forbidden to
me eating, the גמרא Gemara says that makes them two separate objects
and two separate sort of statuses, so I didn't if I only
ate a half a כזית kazayit from this and a half a
כזית kazayit from this I didn't do an act. act of eating
on this and I didn't do an act of eating on this
and since they're separate קונמות konamos why have I violated either קונם?
konam? I said that this apple is forbidden in eating. Did I
eat this apple? No I only took a little taste. Did I
eat this apple? No, right? So how do they combine? So the
גמרא gemara says סוף סוף sof sof זיל הכא ליכא שיעור zil
hacha leka shiur זיל הכא ליכא שיעור zil hacha leka shiur if
you go to one apple you don't have a שיעור, shiur, זיל
הכא ליכא שיעור zil hacha leka shiur you don't have another one
in the other, דאמר אכילה משתיהן עלי קונם. de'amar achila mishteihem alai
konam. Fine, you didn't say them as separate. You used the word
אכילה, achila, you have to to get a כזית kezayit to demand
a כזית, kezayit, but you said the eating of these two apples,
קונם konam these two apples are forbidden to me in eating. So
since you're putting them as a unit, right, then as long as
you did some eating, an eating from some of those two apples,
you know, one or the other or both, you have violated it.
Alright, that explains why they combine, but now why shouldn't they combine
by a שבועה shvua if that's the way you said it? So
the גמרא gemara says דכוותיה גבי שבועה dechavtei gabi shvua
so would you say the same by a שבועה shvua דאמר שבועה
שלא אוכל משתיהן de'amar shvua shelo ochel mishteihem
a שבועה shvua I won't eat from either of these? If that's
true, then if you ate a half a כזית kezayit from each
you should
violate. אמאי אין מצטרפין amai ein mitztarfin why not, why wouldn't they
combine? So אמר רב פנחס amar Rav Pinchas שאני שבועות מתוך שחלוקות
לחטאות אין מצטרפות. shani shvuos mitoch shechalukos lechatos ein mitztarfos.
So now we are going to find, this is going to be
the next משנה. mishna. But the next משנה's mishna going to say
this is a special הלכה halacha by a שבועה. shvua. And actually
what the גמרא gemara does is it shifts, or at least according
to רש"י Rashi it shifts without telling you. If I say שבועה
shvua I won't eat these two apples and I eat a half
a כזית kezayit from each, I would violate. Okay, but apparently what
the גמרא gemara is doing now is it's shifting. There's a space
between saying שבועה shvua I won't eat this, שבועה shvua I won't
eat this, and saying שבועה shvua I won't eat from the two.
The first case they're completely separate. The second case they're completely combined.
What about if I said שבועה shvua I won't eat from this
one and from this one? You get it? I didn't say the
word שבועה shvua by each but I didn't say the two of
them as a unit. שבועה shvua I won't eat from this and
from this. So the משנה's mishna going to say later on, and
let's say forget about combining for a minute, let's say and then
I went ahead and I ate a כזית kezayit from this one
and I ate a כזית kezayit from this
one. The משנה's mishna going to say later on that I bring
two קרבנות, korbanos, which is shocking, right? 'Cause if I ate two
כזיתים kezeitim of חלב, chelev, I would bring one קרבן. korban. So
the חידוש chiddush is that when I say שבועה shvua I won't
eat from this and from this, and I don't even say the
word שבועה shvua again, the חידוש chiddush is that we look at
that as two separate שבועות. shvuos. And if it's two separate שבועות,
shvuos, then they're two different violations. It's like this is חלב chelev
and this is דם. dam. They don't combine to be seen as
one big violation. And therefore, if I eat a כזית kezayit from
this and a כזית kezayit from this, I bring two קרבנות. korbanos.
Okay, that's what it means חלוקה לקרבנות. chaluka lekorbanos. The חידוש chiddush
is that when I say שבועה shvua I won't eat this and
this, we define that as two separate
שבועות. shvuos. The implications are two קרבנות korbanos if you eat a
כזית kezayit of each, and if you eat a half of a
כזית kezayit of each they don't
combine. Whereas if you say קונם konam this and this is forbidden
to me in
eating, it's one קונם. konam. Now we learn it from a פסוק,
pasuk, right? The פסוק pasuk says, רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק pasuk
that's mentioned in the סיפרי, Sifrei, the פסוק pasuk is let me
just check the רש"י, Rashi, it says והיה כי יאשם לאחת מאלה.
vehaya ki yesham leachas me'eleh. Okay.
והיה כי יאשם
לאחת
מאלה.
vehaya ki yesham leachas
me'eleh. So even just one of these. So from there we learn
that if you say שבועה shvua זו וזו zo vezo we define
that as two separate שבועות. shvuos. Okay, so that's even one, like
conceptually we divide it as when you say this and this, if
you say both of them it's one שבועה. shvua. If you say
שבועה shvua this, שבועה shvua this, obviously it's two. But the חידוש
chiddush of this פסוק pasuk is that even if you just say
this and this, שבועה shvua this and this, that we define that
as two separate שבועות. shvuos. So that's the explanation why A there
would be two קרבנות korbanos if it was a כזית kezayit of
each, but why they don't combine when it's a half of a
כזית. kezayit. Okay, לאחת מאלה, leachas me'eleh, excuse me.
Okay.
Alright, so let's take
a look now as the גמרא gemara continues. שאני שבועות מתוך שחלוקות
לחטאות אין מצטרפות shani shvuos mitoch shechalukos lechatos ein mitztarfos since they're
different sin offerings if you say this and this, אין מצטרפות. ein
mitztarfos. אי הכי ei hachi fine, so now we got that idea,
why they combine by a קונם konam and not by a שבועה.
shvua. אי הכי רבי מאיר אומר קונמות כשבועות ei hachi Rabbi Meir
omer konamos keshvuos so wait a minute רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
קונמות konamos also don't combine just like a שבועה shvua doesn't combine.
Why is that? בשלמא שבועות bishlama shvuos I get שבועות shvuos don't
combine, הוו להו חלוקות לחטאות havu lehu chalukos lechatos different sin offerings.
אלא קונמות אמאי לא. ela konamos amai lo. Why shouldn't they combine?
גמרא Gemara says איפוך, ipech, fine, reverse it. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says A is like B, he meant B is like A. רבי
מאיר אומר שבועות כקונמות, Rabbi Meir omer shvuas kikonamos, a שבועה shvua
is like a קונם, konam, they do
combine. וליתיה לרב פנחס, V'laiseih l'Rav Pinchas, he would say yes, רב
פנחס Rav Pinchas you're right, they do bring for different sin offerings
if you say this and this. It is true that that could
lead to two sin offerings, but that's just a חידוש chidush in
like that's a stringency that you bring two sin offerings. It does
not mean they wouldn't combine if you ate a half of a
כזית kezayis of each. If you ate half of a כזית kezayis
of each they actually would combine. Okay. So that's one way of
explaining it. Why do you need a כזית kezayis by קונם? konam?
Because you said the word אכילה. achila. Why is a שבועה shvua
not combined of a half of a כזית kezayis of each? Because
you said this and this and by שבועות shvuas it's combined as
two separate things. And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says I don't do
them as two separate things for שבועות, shvuas, certainly not for the
הלכה halacha of combining. Okay. That's one
answer. רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, רבינא Ravina says כי איתמר דרב פפא
לענין מלקות כי תניא היא לענין קרבן ki itmar d'Rav Pappa l'inyan
malkus ki tanya hi l'inyan korban דבעינן שוה פרוטה. d'baianan shaveh pruta.
So he says like this. He says look, your question was why
do you need to combine by קונם konam if רב פפא Rav
Pappa says a קונם konam is even a כל שהוא? kolshehhu? So
he says here's the difference. A קונם konam is a כל שהוא
kolshehhu for getting מלקות. malkus. You violated your words, you did it
willfully, it's a כל שהוא. kolshehhu. When did he say, when does
this discussion here about combining, that's not about מלקות, malkus, that's about
a קרבן. korban. Now we already know from yesterday's דף daf that
we're reminded that in מלקות malkus we already know this idea, for
example רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says a small amount you get מלקות
malkus if you eat a, you know, whatever, if you eat דם
dam or חלב, cheilev, but you only bring a קרבן korban if
it's a כזית. kezayis. So he says by a קונם, konam, now
remember we mentioned before also there's an impossible idea of מעילה me'ila
by a קונם konam since you're borrowing language of הקדש. hekdesh. So
he says if the question is did I violate my word? Did
I violate the status of this? Did I get מלקות malkus because
I violated the status? The answer is yes, so you get מלקות
malkus even for a כל שהוא. kolshehhu. But do I bring a
קרבן? korban? Now what קרבן? korban? There's no קרבן korban for a
נדר. neder. It's true, there's no קרבן korban for a נדר, neder,
but you know what there's a קרבן korban for? מעילה. Me'ila. If
I treat קונמות konamos as a real הקדש, hekdesh, then I bring
a קרבן korban for מעילה me'ila and a קרבן korban for מעילה
me'ila requires, as we said earlier, a שוה פרוטה. shaveh pruta. So
when we're talking about do קונמות konamos combine, we don't mean for
מלקות. malkus. If you did it intentionally and you didn't say the
word אכילה, achila, you get מלקות, malkus, but you don't bring a
קרבן מעילה korban me'ila unless you have a כזית kezayis a שוה
פרוטה prutah, worth. And that's what we're talking about. קונמות Konamos do
not combine to create a שוה, excuse me, do combine to create
a שוה פרוטה, but שבועה shvua does not. Okay, to create a
כזית kezayit. to bring a
קרבן. korban. Okay, ההוא לענין קרבן דבעינן שוה פרוטה, hahu l'inyan korban
d'baianan shaveh pruta, and that's where you needed קונמות konamos to combine
for the קרבן korban issue. למימר דסברי רבנן, L'meimar d'savri rabbanan, this
would imply if we're talking about a קרבן korban there's not a
קרבן korban for a נדר, neder, so this would imply that the
רבנן rabbanan hold יש מעילה בקונמות, yesh me'ila b'konamos, that there is
מעילה me'ila by a קונם. konam. That's how we could be talking
about a קרבן. korban. But one minute, והתניא, vehatanya, we taught in
a ברייתא: Braisa: כיכר זו הקדש ואכלה, kikar zo hekdesh v'achalah, if
you say this כיכר kikar is הקדש, hekdesh, okay that's not, that's
just הקדש hekdesh for the whole world, that's not a נדר neder
thing, okay, בין הוא בין חבירו מעל, bein hu bein chaveiro ma'al,
you and whether you or somebody else, you do מעילה. me'ila. This
is objectively הקדש. hekdesh. לפיכך יש לו פדיון, L'fichach yesh lo pidyon,
therefore you can redeem it because it's an objective reality that it's
הקדש. hekdesh. כיכר זו עלי הקדש, Kikar zo alai hekdesh, if you
say it's הקדש hekdesh for me, that's creating a subjective reality that's
more in the world of נדר, neder, הוא מעל חבירו לא מעל.
hu ma'al chaveiro lo ma'al. For you to eat it you would
do מעילה, me'ila, for not somebody else. Well that's a bizarre concept
of מעילה. me'ila. That's why it's a question whether there's מעילה me'ila
by קונמות, konamos, because a קונם konam is only a metaphysical reality
vis-a-vis you and we would normally assume for מעילה me'ila it would
need to be הקדש hekdesh as far as everybody is concerned. But
according to this no, there is מעילה me'ila for you not for
your friend. But because it's only a subjective reality, לפיכך אין לה
פדיון דברי רבי מאיר, l'fichach ein lah pidyon divrei Rabbi Meir, רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says you can't redeem it, okay, because it's not
an objective reality. So yes there's מעילה me'ila but it's not objective
enough to redeem it. וחכמים אומרים, V'chachamim omrim, and the חכמים Chachamim
say, בין הוא בין חבירו לא מעל, bein hu bein chaveiro lo
ma'al, no one gets מעילה me'ila for קונמות konamos since it's not
an objective reality. לפי שאין מעילה בקונמות. Lefi she'ein me'ila b'konamos. Okay,
so now there's no מעילה. me'ila. Now the רבנן rabbanan of רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir are saying there's no מעילה, me'ila, but we just
had the רבנן rabbanan and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir debating whether you
can combine for קונמות konamos and we said the combining was to
bring a קרבן, korban, and the only קרבן korban we'd be talking
about is a קרבן מעילה. korban me'ila. So it doesn't work, because
the very רבנן rabbanan that argue on רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say
there is no מעילה me'ila by קונמות konamos and therefore there's no
קרבן. korban. גמרא Gemara says איפוך, ipech, fine, reverse it. Reverse who
says which in terms of whether there's מעילה me'ila by קרבנות. korbanos.
A lot of
reversing. אחד זה ואחד זה לא מעל לפי שאין מעילה בקונמות דברי
רבי מאיר. Echad zeh v'echad zeh lo ma'al lefi she'ein me'ila b'konamos
divrei Rabbi Meir. Have רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir be the one that
says there's no
מעילה. me'ila. Okay. וחכמים אומרים, vechachamim omrim, and the חכמים Chachamim say,
הוא מעל וחברו לא מעל. hu mo'al v'chavero lo mo'al. No, you,
yes there is מעילה, me'ilah, and that's why the rabbis say that
it combines four קונמות konamot because we were talking about a קרבן
korban for less, even a small amount, but for קרבן korban it
combines, okay, for מעילה. me'ilah. That's what we're saying. And the רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir would say like there's no מעילה, me'ilah, so there's
nothing to talk about. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, now we
get why the rabbis say you need an amount because it's מעילה.
me'ilah. But let's understand רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's position in this issue
of combining. אי הכי רבי מאיר אומר קונמות כשבועות, ei hachi Rabbi
Meir omer konamot kishvuot, a קונם konam is like a שבועה, shvuah,
אלא קונמות אצטרופי הוא דלא מצטרפי. ela konamot itztrufei hu d'lo mitztarfei.
So it sounds like when he's saying they're like a שבועה, shvuah,
the same way a שבועה shvuah doesn't combine, a קונם konam doesn't.
So it sounds like רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's whole point is that
there, that you're not going to bring a קרבן korban because they
don't combine. But it sounds like in principle he thinks you could
bring a קרבן. korban. So אצטרופי הוא דלא מצטרפי הא מעילה אית
בהו. itztrufei hu d'lo mitztarfei ha me'ilah it behu. It sounds like
he would be saying that there would be מעילה, me'ilah, but you
just got through by editing the other ברייתא braita to have רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir say there's no מעילה me'ilah by קרבנות. korbanot. So
גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי מאיר אין מעילה בקונמות כלל, amar Rabbi
Meir ein me'ilah bekonamot klal, there's none, there's never מעילה. me'ilah. לדידיהם
דרבנן קאמר. ledideihom derabbanan ka'amar. Fine, he's saying back to the rabbis.
לדידי, ledidi, as far as I'm personally concerned, אין מעילה בקונמות כלל,
ein me'ilah bekonamot klal, there's no מעילה. me'ilah. לדידכו, ledidchu,
אודו לי מיהת דקונמות כשבועות. odu li mihat dekonamot kishvuot. You should
admit to me that a קונם konam is like a שבועה shvuah
and that it doesn't combine in order to bring a קרבן. korban.
ורבנן, verabbanan, and the rabbis say, no. שבועות shvuot doesn't combine איכא
דרב פנחס, ika derav pinchas, because of רב פנחס'ס Rav Pinchas's reason,
because there are separate acts of שבועה. shvuah. קונמות ליתא לדרב פנחס,
konamot leita lederav pinchas, קונמות konamot don't have that. So that was
all very complicated, but the basic upshot is the following: We said
that there's no minimum amount for a קונם. konam. We have a
ברייתא braita that talks about combining, combining to get to a minimum
amount. How do you explain that? One explanation is it's explicitly a
קונם konam that you said the word אכילה achilah with. If you
explicitly say the word אכילה, achilah, there is a minimum amount. Or
this last explanation, there's no minimum amount for a קונם konam for
a מלקות, malkus, but there is a minimum amount for a קרבן
מעילה, korban me'ilah, which would assume, assume that amount would be a
פרוטה, which would assume that there is מעילה me'ilah בקרבנות. bekorbanot. So
according to that, the rabbis would be saying they combine to get,
to get a פרוטה'ס prutah's worth to bring a קרבן מעילה korban
me'ilah by קונם, konam, but they don't combine to get a כזית'ס
kezayit's worth by שבועה. shvuah. שבועה, shvuah, the זה וזה zeh v'zeh
makes things completely separate as we said before. Okay, that's that חידוש
chiddush by שבועה shvuah that they're separate. And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says back, look guys, as far as I'm concerned, you don't bring
a, there's no מעילה me'ilah by קונמות. konamot. It's just a subjective
חפצא cheftza reality, there's no מעילה, me'ilah, there's no קרבן. korban. But
according to you that you think there's a קרבן, korban, you shouldn't
combine the two קונמות. konamot. And the rabbis still say, no, we're
still going to combine it. Okay, fine. So now we get on,
that was, so now we get on back to sort of our
major theme. אמר רבא, amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, שבועה שלא אוכל
ואכל עפר פטור. shvuah shelo ochal v'achal afar patur. So now we
are revisiting things we said before. If somebody says I won't eat
and they eat dirt, they are exempt. Dirt is not generally included
when a person says eat, they mean things that are edible. Now
בעי רבא, ba'ei Rava, now רבא Rava asked, שבועה שלא אוכל עפר,
shvuah shelo ochal afar, somebody explicitly says I won't eat
dirt, בכמה? bechama? כיון דאמר שבועה שלא אוכל, keivan de'amar shvuah shelo
ochal, דעתיה אכזית? daiteih akezayit? Since he used the word אכילה, achilah,
this is according to the rabbis that argue in רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, that when you say a שבועה shvuah of אכילה achilah you
mean a כזית. kezayit? So should we say in this case he
also means a כזית? kezayit. We'll always interpret אכילה achilah as a
כזית. kezayit? או דילמא כיון דלאו מידי דאכלי אינשי הוא, o dilma
keivan delav midi de'achli inshi hu, since dirt is not something normal
people eat, okay, בכל שהוא, bechol shehu, so eating here doesn't have
its normal meaning. Eating here just means putting it in my mouth
and swallowing it, and it wouldn't go by normal definitions. גמרא Gemara
says תיקו, teiku, we don't know. Okay, בעי רבא. ba'ei Rava. We're
going to get to the משנה. mishna. רבא Rava asked, שבועה שלא
אוכל חרצן, shvuah shelo ochal chartzan, בכמה? bechama? Somebody says I won't
eat a grape skin, how much does that mean? כיון דמיתאכיל על
ידי תערובת, keivan demit'achil al yedei ta'arovet, since it is something that
is eaten when it's mixed, when it's on the grape, you eat
a whole grape, so therefore it's a, defined as a normal act
of eating, דעתיה אכזית? daiteih akezayit? So therefore he means normal types
of eating because he sees this in the world of normal food.
או דילמא, o dilma, what if you say, כיון דלאו בעיניה אכלי
ליה אינשי, keivan delav be'eineih achli leh inshi, since people don't eat
it
straight, and he mentioned eating a grape skin which, you know, means
like he's thinking about eating it straight, not in, not together with
the grape. Oh, this says seed. There's actually a question whether חרצן
chartzan means the skin or the seed. Okay, it's interesting they translated
it as the seed. Seed actually would make a little bit more
sense why he's assuming to treat it as non-edible because even though
it's not normal to just eat grape skins, people can do it.
Okay, but there's actually a debate, so it's interesting they translate that
as seed. But that even makes רבא'ס Rava's question a little, a
little sharper, so I appreciate that. Okay, so let's say it means
seed. Okay, so do we say since seeds are normally not edible
by themselves, so therefore it's like the dirt question? So assuming dirt,
this assumes that the answer to dirt was a בכל שהוא. bechol
shehu. Assuming dirt is a בכל שהוא bechol shehu when you say
אכילה, achilah, what if you say אכילה achilah by grape seeds? Is
that like... dirt, and it's a כל שהוא kol shehu because people
don't normally eat it straight? Or do we say since it's eaten
together with the grapes, it's like normal אכילה achila and it goes
by a
כזית? kezayit? Okay. עוד דילמא od dilma כיון דלא בעיני אכלי ליה,
keivan delo beeinei achli lei, you don't eat it straight, אם חזי
דעתיה מהו, im chi da'ateih mahu, even a small amount. תיקו, teiku,
so we don't know. So if dirt was a כל שהוא, kol
shehu, the next question would be what about something like a grape
seed? Would that be a כל שהוא, kol shehu, would that be
a כזית? kezayit בעי רב אשי. ba'ei Rav Ashi. Now רב אשי
Rav Ashi asks: נזיר שאמר שבועה שלא אוכל חרצן בכמה. Nazir she'amar
shvua shelo ochel chartzan bekama. Let's say a
נזיר Nazir says a שבועה shvua that he won't eat a grape
seed. Now a נזיר Nazir is not allowed already to eat a
grape seed. Okay. So this gets back to our point before about
the מושבע ועומד. mushba ve'omeid. דכיון דכזית איסורא דאורייתא הוא, dekeivan dekezayit
issura de'oraita hu,
since he's already forbidden from the תורה Torah to eat a כזית
kezayit, of grape seed, so for this שבועה shvua to mean something
more than what the תורה Torah means, presumably it would have to
mean a כל שהוא. kol shehu. Okay. Otherwise, why is he bothering
to say it? So do we say כי קמשתבע אהיתירא קמשתבע, ki
kamishtava aheiteira kamishtava,
so he's making a שבועה shvua to something that's now not forbidden
by the תורה, Torah, ודעתיה אמהו? veda'ateih amahu? So because the תורה
Torah already forbids a כזית, kezayit? we're going to interpret his words
to mean a כל שהוא, kol shehu, otherwise it would be purposeless,
or we'll assume that's what he meant. או דילמא, od dilma, or
do we say כיון דאמר שלא אוכל, keivan de'amar shelo ochel, since
he just used the generic word שלא אוכל, shelo ochel, דעתיה אכזית,
da'ateih akezayit, he's talking about a כזית? kezayit תא שמע, ta shema,
come and hear. שבועה שלא אוכל ואכל נבילות וטריפות שקצים ורמשים. shvua
shelo ochel ve'achal neveilot utreifot shkatzim uremasim. This is easy because now
it's review of what we heard before. Somebody says a generic 'I
won't eat' and they eat like חזיר, chazer, חייב, chayav, because that's
included in eating. רבי שמעון פוטר. Rabbi Shimon poter. ואווינן בה, vavinan
bah, and we asked, אמאי חייב? amai chayav? Why are you חייב
chayav even if eating חזיר chazer is an act of eating, but
מושבע ועומד מהר סיני הוא? mushba ve'omeid meHar Sinai hu? You're already
foresworn from הר סיני. Har Sinai. רב ושמואל ורבי יוחנן דאמרי בכולל
דברים המותרין עם דברים האסורין, Rav uShmuel veRabbi Yochanan de'amri becholel devarim
hamutarim im devarim ha'asurin, they all say that you say 'I won't
eat everything', so since it applies to kosher food, it also applies
to non-kosher food. וריש לקיש אמר, veReish Lakish amar, and וריש לקיש
Reish Lakish says: אי אתה מוצא אלא אי במפרש חצי שיעור ואליבא
דרבנן. ei ata motzei ela ei bimefaresh chatzi shiur ve'aliba deRabbanan. No,
no, no. Even if you say everything, it wouldn't include treif food
because treif food is already forbidden. The only way you're going to
get treif food included in your שבועה shvua is if you explicitly,
if your שבועה shvua refers to something that's not already forbidden to
you. So what would be the example? You explicitly said 'I won't
eat a half of a כזית kezayit, of חזיר'. chazer So then
since factually you're not forbidden in that, I mean whatever, it's not
the same biblical violation, there the שבועה shvua would take effect. Okay.
אי אתה מוצא אלא אי במפרש חצי שיעור ואליבא דרבנן. ei ata
motzei ela ei bimefaresh chatzi shiur ve'aliba deRabbanan. You explicitly say a
half כזית, kezayit then it would take effect. אי בסתם ואליבא דרבי
עקיבא, ei bistan ve'aliba deRabbi Akiva, or for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
you don't have to say a half כזית kezayit because רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, any שבועה shvua that you won't eat means even a
small amount. דאמר אדם אוסר עצמו בכל שהוא. de'amar adam oser atzmo
bechol shehu. Okay, fine. So now though, we get back to the
question of: should we naturally interpret your words to mean something that,
that makes it like meaningful? Okay, that means... so the question is...
because the question that בעי רב אשי ba'ei Rav Ashi asked is
if a נזיר Nazir says 'I won't eat grape seed', maybe we
should naturally interpret that to mean a half of a כזית kezayit.
in order that it should be something meaningful, since he's already anyway
forbidden in a כזית. kezayit, So this makes it clear that we
wouldn't naturally say that. You have to be explicit. If you're not
explicit, then we say you're just redundant and the שבועה shvua doesn't
take effect. Okay.
So
the גמרא Gemara says: והא נבילה דמושבע ועומד מהר סיני הוא. veha
neveila demushba ve'omeid meHar Sinai hu. נבילה, neveila, you're already foresworn. דכי
חרצן לגבי נזיר דמי, dechi chartzan legabei Nazir dami,
and that's just like the grape seed for the נזיר. Nazir. And
we don't say, 'Oh, since obviously you're already forbidden in חזיר, chazer,
you must mean a half of a כזית, kezayit you must mean
a כל שהוא.' kol shehu. We don't say that. We say since
you weren't explicit, you mean a כזית kezayit. and it's redundant and
it doesn't take
effect. הטעמא דפירש. hata'ama defireish. The only way your שבועה shvua on
a חזיר, chazer, according to וריש לקיש Reish Lakish at least, would
take effect is if you explicitly said a half of a כזית.
kezayit. הא לא פירש דעתיה אכזית. ha lo peireish da'ateih akezayit. If
you don't explicate, you mean a כזית. kezayit. And we don't... so
even though it's redundant, we don't say 'Oh, since it's going to
be redundant, let's explain it in a way that's not redundant.' We
don't say that. We say, yes, it's redundant and it doesn't take
effect. So therefore שמע מינה, shma mina, you can hear
from... אלא תפשוט דבעי רבא. ela tifshot deba'ei Rava. So there, let's
conclude רבא's Rava question. שבועה שלא אוכל עפר בכמה? shvua shelo ochel
afar bekama? A שבועה shvua that I won't eat dirt, how much?
תפשוט דעד דאיכא כזית. tifshot dead de'ika kezayit. Let's compare that to
the נבילה neveila case. Okay, forget the מושבע ועומד mushba ve'omeid aspect.
If a guy says 'I won't eat נבילה' neveila explicitly, שבועה shvua
'I won't eat נבילה', neveila we say it means a כזית. kezayit,
Well, isn't נבילה neveila like dirt? Because they're both not in the
edible category. Now there's an obvious answer. דנבילה כעפר דמיא. deneveila ke'afar
damya. נבילה neveila is something that's not edible if you're a
Halachic Jew. הטעמא דפירש. hata'ama defireish. And only when you say explicitly
a half of a כזית, kezayit. you mean a half of a
כזית. kezayit. הא לא פירש דעתיה אכזית. ha lo peireish da'ateih akezayit.
So even though נבילה neveila isn't edible, when you use the word
'eat', you mean a כזית. kezayit? So dirt isn't edible, so when
you use the word 'eat', shouldn't you mean a כזית? k'zayis. So
גמרא Gemara says it's an obvious difference. לאו בר—no. lav bar עפר
לאו בר אכילה הוא כלל. Afar lav bar achila hu klal. Dirt
is inedible like as a biological process, okay? נבלה בר אכילה. Neveilah
bar achila. A נבלה neveilah is something that is edible. Look at
99.9% of the world. ואריה דרביע עליה. Va'aryeh d'ravia ileiha. There's just
a lion crouching upon it, meaning the תורה Torah is telling you
don't do it. But in terms of the physical nature of the
object, it's edible. So when you use the word eat, you mean
a כזית. k'zayis. Eat for edible objects means a כזית. k'zayis That
doesn't answer our question whether what eat means in the context of
dirt. Does that mean a כזית or does that mean a כל
שהוא? kol shehu? And we don't have an answer to that, but
we will pick up with the משנה, mishna, the next משנה mishna
tomorrow.